{
  "reference_number": "9107",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes but only if well reviewed, and broadly acknowledged climate science results indicate a change in target can safely be made."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Tackling most impacted industries and communities first to provide time to implement path to adaptation. Providing sufficient\n\nresearch funding and incentives early on to encourage local innovation and entrepreneurial opportunities in meeting requirements.\nExpand our green manufacturing and green tech sectors. Establish public-owned green tech incubator investment fund to assist\n\ninnovators to bring green products, services, methods & processes to market while retaining ownership in New Zealand. Investment\nreturns required to be directed toward green investments, research, education, or appropriate improvements in under served\n\ncommunities. Ongoing consultation, similar to this submission process, on options for meeting budgets. Providing reskilling\nprograms or incentives for employers to provide the same. Putting high priority on agricultural research to be the world leader in\n\ngreen farming."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Generally agree. Regarding business and technological expertise: these are more than desirable, but they concern subsidiary\n\nconsiderations. That is, we always want to make decisions that make the most of business and technical opportunities up to a point.\nThat point is that we meet our emissions targets which are set based on science not profit concerns."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Include research on low tech / appropriate tech solutions thereby providing for local community resilience and reduced\nenvironmental impact of solutions (high tech has more unforseen consequences.) Consider military preparedness for increased\n\nresource-based conflicts especially in Pacific. Increase diplomatic work and joint planning with other nations to reduce likelihood of\nresource-based conflicts particularly where we could be drawn in through traditional alliances. Consider how to build internal\n\neconomy so country can better weather downturns in export and especially tourist sectors."
    }
  ]
}
